<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- RSS generated by Radio UserLand v8.0.5 on 9/30/2002; 4:00:00 AM Pacific -->
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:blogChannel="http://backend.userland.com/blogChannelModule">
    <channel>
        <title>Indie Tech Summit Videos</title>
        <link>https://ind.ie/summit/videos</link>
        <description>A weblog about scripting and stuff like that.</description>
        <language>en-gb</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 10:56:00 BST</lastBuildDate>
        <ttl>60</ttl>
        <item>
            <title>Brave New World</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#BraveNewWorld</link>
            <description>In the opening session of the Indie Tech Summit, Aral Balkan welcomes us to the Schnail Mail office. He presents a terrifying glimpse into the near future, before discussing what can be done to avoid it. Aral shares with us his vision for an alternative future, filled with beautiful, independent technology; where the devices and services we use both empower us as individuals, and respect our fundamental human rights.</description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 10:56:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Richard Stallman Interview</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#RichardStallmanInterview</link>
            <description>Richard Stallman and Aral Balkan discuss Free Software, offering insight into the fundamental importance of its existence, how it differs from proprietary alternatives and why this matters. Going on to consider the Open Source movement, Richard explains why he sees mere openness as insufficient and how this ethics-free alternative can be detrimental to the fight for freedom. Concluding with a lively Q&amp;A session between Richard and the audience.</description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 10:56:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Laura Kalbag on Universal Design</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#LauraKalbag</link>
            <description>In this talk on accessibility, Laura Kalbag explains why accessible design is not just a simple matter of wheelchairs and screen readers, but something which can and does benefit us all. Framing it instead as ‘inclusive design’ or ‘universal design’, Laura shows us just how fundamental accessibility is to creating sustainable products, and why we all need to consider it, in every product we create.</description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 15:56:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Cole Peters, First Things First</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#ColePeters</link>
            <description>First Things First 2014 Project leader, Cole Peters, talks about the roles and responsibilities of the designer. Highlighting the immense power of the products we create, he discusses the need for greater social and ethical consideration from those who make design, and therefore communication, their practice.</description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 12:00:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Ivanka Majic on Design in Traditional Free and Open Source</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#IvankaMajic</link>
            <description>UX Designer, Ivanka Majic, discusses the need for clear communication and shared vision in design, and suggests that it is the lack of these factors, not malice or apathy, which leads to failures in design. </description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 12:00:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Lena Reinhard on Designing Diversity</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#LenaReinhard</link>
            <description>Lena Reinhard talks about diversity and highlights the many benefits that come from building organisations and institutions which represent a broad spectrum of society. In order to create the free and independent web society needs, diversity, Lena concludes, is non-negotiable.</description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 12:00:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Cole Peters, Ivanka Majic, Laura Kalbag, Lena Reinhard, with questions from participants.</title>
            <link>http://ind.ie/summit/videos/#DesigningIndependence</link>
            <description>Cole Peters, Ivanka Majic, Laura Kalbag and Lena Reinhard take questions from the audience, and discuss the interrelated nature of their own specialist areas of design.</description>
            <guid isPermaLink="true"></guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 12:00:00 BST</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>